A large machine like ours
could cost even a couple of
billion for an object that then provides
energy for 60 years.   An
intuition, a choice, something that
maybe you were right, others
were
very wrong.   I
've raised a billion dollars so far
.   I
have no idea how low
the market might have fallen.  What do we mean?  trillions.
First, the first step is to have a mind that
can give authorization.  This is
the purpose [music] of the law.  There are
still
many things that can be done with radioactivity.  They can make batteries that
have virtually infinite lives.   I do
n't work exaggeratedly 16 hours a day, 7
days a week.
What do you visualize as saying I grit my teeth?   It
still continues because that is
the goal.  [music] It
's not that I have to grit my teeth, I
'm unstoppable.
He is Stefano Buono and he is the entrepreneur
who wants to bring nuclear power back to
Italy.  After selling his first
company for nearly $4 billion, 3A set
sail on his catamaran around
the world and from there launched
Nucleo, a nuclear energy company that
has raised over $1 billion to date
.  he sailed the seas
for a year and a half, as he had already wanted to
do in 1993, when Carlo Rubia,
Nobel Prize winner for physics, called him to
work with him at CERN on a new
type of safer nuclear reactor, the
Rubietron.  The project, however, failed and
he continued to work as a physicist
on the particle accelerator from which he
later launched his first company, 3A,
specialized in PET, which
I talked about in the video dedicated to CERN.
However, Stefano couldn't stomach the failure of Rubiatron,
so after
selling 3A and collecting around 200
million from the exit, he decided to go
all in on nuclear power with a core.
However, the undertaking is not simple.  On the one
hand, nuclear power is unviable in Italy
, even though the Chamber of Deputies recently
approved a bill enabling a return
to energy production from this
source. On the other hand, a
lot of money is needed anyway.  Which is why Nucleo has
announced that it will list on the Nasdaq
by the end of this year with a
preliminary valuation of $2.4 billion
.  The listing will take place through a
SPAC, that is, through a merger with
a listed company, and this
could happen very soon.
The company was born with the idea of ​​listing
on the NASDAQ, so it was the
right time because American policy had changed about a year ago
.  We had
European technology that could be
used in Europe, but not in the
United States, because the United States
has blocked the recycling of
nuclear fuel for 50 years.  Our
fuel is based on
recycled material and is then reused in the
reactors.  It can be reused many
times.  They changed their policy a year ago
, so we became a
coup, a very attentive company for
them.  To be listed on the Nasdaq, it's good
to be an innovative company, have
good technology, but you also need to have
operations in the United States, so
until a year ago we couldn't do that at
all, so we worked in
parallel to bring this technology
to the United States, but also to prepare for
a listing.  Why Spacc?  Because
this is a faster way to
become a public company on the markets,
and since we will be dealing with
fairly sensitive material, we are the first
company in the world that will ever receive
plutonium for civilian purposes and to make
nuclear fuel.  They were happy for us to do it
either with an
American partner or as an American company.  We
partnered with OCRO
and then tried to dress up as
Americans as best we could, and
becoming a Nasdaq-listed company
is a great way to get some
American investors on board
and thus Americanize ourselves a little bit.
So America is also a potential
customer now.
Yes, the idea of ​​building a
fuel factory is to be able to serve
our constituents.  We had an
industrial plan that included the possibility
of building around twenty reactors in
England, which was the country where
we were born, but England had
changed its policy in the opposite direction.
He had decided not to reuse the plutonium he had extracted from the radioactive waste to make new fuel
, but to put it underground.
This had disappointed us quite a bit,
so we decided to change the
industrial plan, no longer building 20 reactors and
a fuel factory in
England, but to do it in the
United States.
Doing diptech costs a lot of money.
Why is so much capital needed?
We brought together 900 people
to license a new
nuclear reactor.  There are probably
thousands of documents to be given.  Every
document of the technology, drawings,
calculations,
safety demonstrations.  There are companies that have
spent a few hundred million
dollars to get to the point of having
licenses.  Then you have to build it.  A
large machine like ours could
cost even a couple of billion because
a lot of components are built for the first time
which then become
industrial components, so the price
goes down.  I immediately wanted to verticalize
our supply chain as much as possible
to make us independent from any
external events.  We've made three
acquisitions of companies that generated
revenue, already had a
commercial presence in the nuclear field, and among other things,
these companies have allowed us
to record $80 million in
revenue in 2024. With them, we want to
build the most important components
of our reactors, those where not only
is the intellectual property involved, but
we also need to retain a little bit of
know-how, also because what
we will be doing is selling the reactors, not
using them.  In Slovakia we have a
49% partnership with the Slovak government to build
four reactors, but in general
we want to sell the technology.  The
technology is sold through licenses and
the consumables for the
fuel are sold, so it is an approach that
must last more than 60 years, which is the life
of a reactor.
Nucleo has not yet built a
full-fledged nuclear reactor, but
plans have already begun.  For example,
the company closed a
€3.2 billion deal to build reactors
in Slovakia.  But even more than
turnover, the important thing in this
business is credibility.  You must
demonstrate that you are capable of
building a
functioning and safe nuclear reactor within the established timeframe and
budget.  For this reason
Nucleo has built a
demonstration non-nuclear reactor in an
ENEA facility on Lake Brasimone between Bologna
and Florence.  However, it will take some time before the first
nuclear reactor is fully operational
, both for
regulatory reasons, as in the case of Italy,
and for construction times, which in the
case of the first reactor will be
longer, around 5 years.  Another challenge
is sourcing resources and
protecting
technological breakthroughs, which is why
Nucleo has acquired three supply
chain companies.  How much does a
brand new reactor cost to manufacture, and how much does
the cost drop once it's
industrialized?  Let's say a prototype is
expected to cost about $10 per
installed watt, [music] so 200 MW like
ours is billions and it would be a
dream for the reactor manufacturer if
this cost is then halved.  $5 a
watt becomes a very competitive price
for an object that then provides energy
93% of the time continuously 24 hours a day,
7 days a week, throughout the year for 60
years.  It could last more than 60 years,
or
there are some reactors whose lifespan is
extended up to 80 years, and the AI ​​is thinking of
extending the lifespan of many reactors up to
100.
The core reactors have a power
of 200 MW, but since they are modular, it is
possible to plan for one or more reactors
depending on the energy needs.  To
give you an idea, if we wanted to meet
Rome's energy needs for a
year, we would need approximately six
reactors. What's the total cost of paperwork, such
as licenses and compliance
?  a lot and it is perhaps
the biggest challenge that
the nuclear industry faces.  The fight against this
type of overcost was
certainly undertaken by the United States because
they have released a new
licensing regulation that significantly simplifies the situation.
I have my doubts that this type of
philosophy is easily transportable
to Europe at the moment, but we
tend to do exactly the opposite, to
complicate and regulate everything.  Returning
to the stock market listing, this will
translate into new capital entering
the company.  How will
this capital be used?
Obviously we want to finish our
10 MW brazier electric demonstration reactor.  It's a somewhat
special reactor because it's obviously not
nuclear—nuclear power isn't allowed in Italy—
so the reactor is heated
electrically.  Everything else is very
similar to what a final reactor is
, we are even installing
a turbine and it is in fact perhaps
the only industrial demonstrator of a
reactor that actually generates
electricity as well as consuming it.  Operating
this reactor for 5 years will also provide
indications on the
long-term reliability of the components. We could
bring it to temperatures much higher
than the
reactor's steady-state operation, thus testing
new materials, new solutions, so
there is a lot to learn.  Today a
reactor is made through calculations,
very little experimentation is done.  When you move
from a PowerPoint to the real thing,
you obviously encounter problems
that you couldn't foresee beforehand and you learn
to solve them.  But today Nucleo is
listed on the Nasdaq at a valuation of 2.4 billion
without even having one of
their products actually in operation.   How come
?
The fact that there isn't an
operational machine that works right now does
n't mean we're not on the
market because we've made a deal
with Slovakia and are finalizing
a series of agreements with other companies
that need rectors.  You don't
build it and pay for it in the end, you pay for it
before you conceive it with a license
etc.  This is why we
need a demonstration plant,
because even if it's not nuclear,
this plant demonstrates that
our company is capable of conceiving,
designing, procuring, building the
components, commissioning a reactor, and
making it operational—in the case
of Bresimone, for example, within a year—while also
maintaining the set budget, and this
is one of the criticisms of nuclear power,
right?  Go over budget.
Outside the budget it costs much more, but
only two recent examples are still sold,
the Finnish one, the French one
in Europe which were started to be
built before the
Fukushima accident, which have undergone all this
drama of the rule changes,
the Issensing etc.  So let's imagine
that if someone designs a
reactor, then while it's being built
the rules change, everything has to change
and maybe they don't think that for example
France from '74 to '90, so in 16 years,
built 50 nuclear reactors.
In Europe, too, we are capable of building
reactors quickly and efficiently.
Then let's not talk about China which
now builds 5-6 of them a year.   It
also makes you understand the weight of the
paperwork, again not only on costs,
but also on time, because if you remove the
nuclear part, suddenly
it becomes easier to build, it
takes a year and no longer 3 years.
Exact.  But even the number n will be
completely different from the first.  We're
thinking of building the first one in maybe 5
years, but the goal is to build it in
three, the ambition is to even do it in
two.  Clearly, tying up capital
for 17 years, as in the worst
nuclear projects, was a tragedy.  But
if someone immobilizes capital for 2
years, then makes it productive for 60, it is
a production plant that
will certainly be very competitive.
In a dream scenario, in 10 years,
how many reactors have been built?   About
ten of us.
And what are the things that could
prevent this?
very particular external geopolitical events,
lack of money to do so.  I believe
that there is a lot of money around the
world, that there is a massive need for this type of
energy.  There's a lot of talk
about data centers, but that's just the tip of
the iceberg.  Under the iceberg is all
the industry that needs
low-cost energy that has suffered as
gas costs have
skyrocketed.  Many industries
even had to suspend production
so as not to make a loss by doing so.
Since I believe that not only
our project, but probably others as well,
will have a very attractive economic profile
for this type of
investment, there will be a lot of money.   Are
there any bureaucratic and
legislative issues that need to be changed to
achieve the goal you mentioned?
Like today in Italy it's technically not
possible to do.
In Italy, the first step is to have an agency
that can grant authorization.  This
is the goal of the law that is being
approved in recent weeks.  The
law provides for some
acceleration.  For example, if the
rector has had a license in
another country, an accelerated process may occur
.  Let me give you an example: we
have made great progress in
French licensing.  Slovakia has
decided to abide by the French license
and will therefore give us an accelerated path.
In the United States.  By law, ENRC,
the regulatory body that issues licenses,
must now respond to
a license application within 18 months.  This would be
a reasonable time.  Yes, a category
of reactors that I don't know belongs to can no
longer have a nuclear accident by
design and for intrinsic
physical reasons like the accidents of the past and
therefore do not represent a problem for
the environment or for people and the
United States has decided not to proceed with an
environmental authorization for
this type of reactor.  The
plane crash, a reactor must withstand
the impact of a passenger plane
entering vertically above the roof of the
reactor, is perhaps a bit of an exaggeration.
This super-bureaucracy is a mirror
of a popular culture that has survived
decades of psychological terrorism.
Absolutely because young people,
not having the bias of the past for many
years, are not permeated by this type of culture,
so they approach the
problem in a much more practical way.
Perhaps many people don't know this, but in Italy,
from the 1960s to the 1980s, electricity was produced
from nuclear power.  Then in
1986 there was the Chernobyl disaster and
the following year a referendum sanctioned the end
of this energy source.  In 2011 there
was another referendum to try to
return to nuclear power, but that same year
a tsunami caused an accident at the
Fukushima nuclear power plant.  The
referendum did not pass.  In the past, the issue
of decarbonisation was not so
current and oil and gas prices
were lower, so
the issue of nuclear power was not felt as urgent.  Now,
however, the context has changed, from
climate change which is becoming
increasingly relevant to the wars in
Ukraine and Iran which have caused
gas prices to skyrocket and for
this reason the talk of
nuclear power has returned.  While I was recording this
interview, the
House of Representatives was debating the bill on
this matter, which was subsequently
approved.  The next steps are
approval by the Senate and then within a
year the government will have to approve one or
more decrees regulating
nuclear power.  The Energy Minister has
declared that the first permits
for the construction of nuclear power plants
could arrive by 2030. The
topic of nuclear power
has become highly politicized in recent decades,
and the generation before mine
suffered years and years of
unjustified psychological terrorism.  However, if we look at
the data, nuclear power is currently among the
safest, cleanest,
and cheapest energy sources.  Just look at the
scientific data or the dozens [music] of
videos on YouTube that summarize the topic.
From the problem of waste, which in reality
is extremely safe and produced in
much smaller quantities for the same amount of energy
produced compared to the pollution from
many other energy sources, or
safety, where accidents that have never
even caused casualties have much
more resonance than all the other
casualties linked to other
energy sources.  Let's go back to you more as an
entrepreneur and a scientist, which is a mix
that often intrigues me because maybe
I'm used to talking only with
researchers—I made a video
inside CERN and they only think about
that and have no idea perhaps of the
business applications of their
discoveries—or I talk to entrepreneurs
who know nothing about science, but
look at the balance sheets and maybe hire scientists
.  How do you feel about having both
roles?  It is important to be a
moderator between the two worlds.  If I think
back a little, when I started my
first company, which was a biotech company,
we also analyzed about 200
possibilities for licensing
technological innovations.  Then,
in my life as an investor, I also created
a company that invests in innovation,
Lft, which we are now transforming into an
Evergreen fund that has invested in more
than 60 totally innovative companies.
Clearly the researcher has
serious difficulties in understanding whether his
innovation can even find a
market, because the typical mentality is to
think that ah it works better, it's
smarter, it has these advantages, therefore
it's a product that [music] will be
successful?  Absolutely not.  I
found myself having to mediate the ambitions of
researchers who had patents;
they thought that the patent was the
end of a journey, not
the beginning of a journey.  If the
core company was able to grow so
quickly, it was because I had the experience
of an entrepreneur in a subject I have been
working on since 1993, where I worked
exclusively for 9 years as a
researcher, which I then followed
very closely both as a company and
personally.  I realized that
at Triana, my previous company,
I had gone through a personal journey where
I finally knew all the
market players, I had spoken to all
our competitors, partners, etc.
I'm still perhaps halfway through
the nuclear journey.
What are the typical mistakes made by a
smart, ambitious PhD who then
crashes into the market?  Thinking that the
product will sell at the speed it
deserves and not at the speed it will have on the
market.  Since a product has reached
a certain stage of development, it is
not actually finished.  Considering a product
finished and ready for the market
often takes much longer than one
thinks or
plans.
What were the mistakes you made along the way?  There were
many, but none of these mistakes had a
significant impact on our
path [music], so I have to say I was
very lucky.
I've definitely taken longer routes.
When you innovate, hitting dead ends is
part of the game.
The important thing is not to have lost the course
of your business strategy.  Many
people I met, especially
at my last company, may not have been the
right people for the role I
gave them, especially since the speed with which
we developed the core team was
multiple times faster than the previous one.
I had to go even faster.
We probably spent money we
shouldn't have, hired people we
shouldn't have, but when you
want to move quickly,
inefficiency is by design.  Exact.  But I do
n't recommend everyone to do
this, on the contrary.  I would advise more
caution, after my experience, than
saying "Let's do it the American way, money
is not a problem, we raise money,
we spend it as much as we can."
On the contrary, an intuition, a choice,
something that maybe you were right,
others were
very wrong.
For example, fuel choices.
At the beginning of the 21st century, making MOX was
more expensive than making uranium fuels
.  Fuel recycling was
much more expensive, it was much more
difficult because you had to have
plutonium and not everyone gives them
plutonium.  I bet everything on this
two days after Russia's invasion of Ukraine
because, being on the
market and frequenting
market players, it was immediately clear to me
that the only supplier of
20% enriched urium that
we and many other companies needed was
Russia, that the investments were
high, that it would take years, which
were usually state investments.
So I said to myself, but since the
difficulty of having a fuel
becomes the same for me, but my
fuel can be more sustainable,
let's go and aim everything at the max.  And
it paid off for us because after
four years we are the only company in the world
that has the design of a factory for
this type of fuel already ready and
we have discovered that the costs now of
producing our fuel are
much lower than the projected costs
of the fuel that other players in
small advanced nuclear reactors
have to bear.
The core's flagship product is a
small modular nuclear reactor, in
jargon called SMR, Small Modular
Reactor.  It is a
fourth-generation nuclear reactor, which means it
has a high level of safety because
the reactor is built in such a way that
certain accidents cannot
physically occur.  In particular,
the core reactor is a
fast reactor, cooled by lead,
exactly as was attempted with
the Rubietron.  Lead has several
advantages.  A very high boiling point of
1743°,
radiation shielding properties and little reactivity to water and
air.  The fuel chosen is MOX,
a mixture of urium and plutonium oxides
that, once exhausted, can be
reprocessed to extract new
fuel while reducing the amount of
waste.  In short, this is how a reactor of this
type works.  The nuclear reaction
in MOX produces heat that is used
to produce steam, which turns
a turbine that produces
electricity.  This applies to all
ways of producing energy.  Something
heats up, turns a turbine that
produces energy.  To prevent the
core from reaching too
high temperatures, lead is used as a
coolant.  Today there are
20-year-olds who are trying to start a
business and are already thinking about exiting, and
then there are entrepreneurs like you who,
despite having had great
success, instead of stopping, decide
to take on another challenge—and not just
any challenge, but a very long-
term challenge.  What drives this
relentless struggle you wage?  In the first
experience it was seeing a product
that could do good, a
therapeutic product that was poorly used,
poorly distributed, poorly understood,
etc., could be brought to
market and therefore also the impact
this could have.  Obviously, after the
first exit, the economic aspect no
longer makes sense, and unfortunately I once again saw
an innovation that had been possible for 20 years
: the lead reactor,
which recycled the fuel and
eliminated the problem of waste,
geological deposits, etc., that
no one had ever pursued.  I
realized that thanks to my reputation,
my financial support, including the
company's startup, and my connections
as a scientist and entrepreneur,
I could actually change this
status, and so I wanted to
complete this work that I had
ideally begun in 1993 when
I was a very young researcher at the
Cardinal.
It's tiring to carry on this
battle, right?
It's quite tiring, right?  I did
n't exaggerate, but I worked 16 hours a day, 7
days a week.
What do you visualize as stringent,
continue because that's
the goal.  [music] I
don't suffer from working so much because there's an
adrenaline rush, there's the desire to do it, it's
not that I have to grit my teeth,
luckily my way of being, that is, I
'm unstoppable, I can't stay
still.  My mother used to say that one thing is worth a hundred
.
But what's the thing about your job that gives you the most
adrenaline?  Which one
is the one that perhaps bores you?
Finance bores me with numbers, advances,
balance sheets,
the CFO who I do
n't want to know anything about.
This cannot be done.
Yes, he doesn't try.  No, I'm kidding.  I have to say
that we changed CF three times, so
I had to take a little interest in the
matter.
And on the contrary, what's the part you like?
On the contrary, business development,
making deals is great fun, meeting
people, new technologies, making
alliances, partnerships.
What talents are you struggling to
find in the company you're looking for?  manager.
Many managers who have worked in
large companies think about their own
budget, their own people, etc. They
don't have a global vision of what
the company needs to do, and this is
difficult to find.  When you find
the right people you move forward at the
speed of light.
What are the green flags that you say he
has to be a good person to
bring in?
Strategic vision is very
important, but it's a bit of a feeling.
Motivation is very important.  Red
flag, let's say, if someone talks about
salaries or working hours, it's not
for us.
You're looking for extrinsic motivation, so
someone who works here for
Yes, of course they have to come to work for
what we do, not for how much they
earn or where they have to spend their
time.
Out of 900 people, do you think you managed
to have a good balance of
motivated people?  Yes, but obviously I'm a
physicist, so I know there are queues in
every distribution.  In short,
Stefano could
retire and send his children,
grandchildren, and great-grandchildren into retirement, but instead he has decided
to dedicate himself 24/7 to a project that he is
passionate about and that could change the
world, so he expects the same
level of passion from those who work with him.
How many days do you spend in Italy and how many
traveling?
I spend 53% of my time in Italy, the
rest traveling.
53 how did you calculate it?
With an app.  Oh, yeah, [laughter] I've had it
since this year, so I'm
talking about 2026.
But did you do that on purpose because you wanted to
track this aspect?
Yes, because they make me pay taxes in
practically every country I set foot in.  So
I thought you only paid taxes where you
were resident.
And I thought so too.  Then I discovered a
whole world.  If you are a
U.S. resident, you should technically
pay taxes in each U.S. state
for the prorated time you spend there.
Incredible.
When you're in Italy, are you mostly in the
office or do you also travel around Italy?  No, I
also travel around Italy.  Absolutely.  We have
many locations.  We have offices in Genoa,
Piombino, Bologna, and Rome.  There are currently two factories
in Italy, one in
Piombino and the other in Rome.
The one you have acquired.
Yes. One is new because we've
rented it for the moment because we have
growing capacity, but we've
doubled the
factory space in Piombino, for example.  Then we
obviously have the Bologna office, but also
the Brasimone presence which is truly
very important and then we have built
several laboratories here in Turin where
we have very
sophisticated equipment.  We have one of the two most
powerful electron microscopes in Europe, which can
even see the structure of the
crystalline lens, that is, the atoms one by
one.
This also opens us up to providing more and
more services to other companies.
We just won an air tender for
the smelting plant.  We will help you
design a small piece of the process.  We
hope so.  We won a tender in
Romania to build a lead laboratory
, to build the lead reactor
in Romania as well.  Four tenders which, when
added together, will generate a turnover
of 53 million euros over the next 2-3
years.
During your typical
office days, how many meetings do you have?  How does it
work?  Unfortunately, we live in
such a virtual world that I often find myself in
front of the computer in the office having
meetings, especially since
we have a presence in six other countries besides Italy.  Here
in the office I can maybe have
lunch, meet people who
pass by, but the office day isn't dedicated
to meetings.
How many carries do you have?  maybe twenty or
so because it's a company that's
innovating at the beginning and so having the
situation under control is quite
important.  Honestly, if the ports are
independent, they are not a burden, maybe
some need a little more
presence, it depends on the degree of
independence.  I want to lead them to
total independence.
What are the functions?  They are all
important, but the ones that are
the most important for you, [music]
so you have to pay attention to them.
I spend a lot of time in public affairs because of
the nature of the business.  My
previous business didn't even have a single person
dealing with government affairs.   I
had never met a minister, I
had never met anyone, nor did I
need to.
Now you're almost a minister, let's say.
Now I have a minister's agenda.
Yes, we have to meet with many
ministers in every country where we operate or
even in countries where we don't operate, where
we go to operate.  I really like
communication, and communication in the
case of nuclear power is again a little
different because it is obviously
corporate communication, but perhaps more
than corporate communication, communication
towards stakeholders and the
public is truly very
important because I really care that
nuclear power is not perceived as
something dangerous, expensive,
etc., but rather perceived for what it
is: a technology that humanity
needs and cannot do without.  I dedicate a
lot of time, even if I almost shouldn't,
let's say, maybe even too much,
to podcasts, to these things
, but it's important.  Then the company
really needs money, I've raised a
billion dollars so far, perhaps
the record for meetings is the one with
investors.
How do you convince an investor to
bet on this match and maybe
get you to give them 100 million euros?
The business must be liked, the business
model must be convincing, and people must be
convincing.  When I have to invest
70% of the value in people and
20% in the business model.
Technology matters little, almost if you think
about a product or a technology that is not
perfected, a good team can
carry it forward.  A bad team
will fail even with the best
technology in the world.   Do
you have any real competitors today? Have they
emerged?
Absolutely not.  in the sense that the
market is so vast, so
vast that
we will not be able to serve it for at least two decades.  So under these
conditions there are no competitors.  There is
more to collaborate with those who operate in
this market rather than
compete.
Maybe the day comes when you are
saturating the market, it would be a
happy problem.  It means you have a turnover of
hundreds of billions.
Yes, yes.  However, in the end it will
still be marked by a few players in which
each will have found its
happy niche which is more optimised
in its own technology or which
derives from the relationships it has in the countries
in which it operates etc.  So there's a
product that my phone is nicer
than yours and then after 7 months
everything changes, I become more advanced than you,
etc.  There is no such
competition, the dynamics are so
long.
You said earlier, "The market is so big,
I have no idea how big
the market can be."  What do we mean?  Trillions.
Trillions.
Yes.
Well, at least as much as oil and gas.
Absolutely what we want
to replace,
which is even more because the
energy demand in the next few decades is
exponential.
If you didn't have to start a new company, if you were
forced not to start this company,
what would you do?  Tomorrow you will reach my
sailboat and you will start again.  I mean, no,
I never abandoned it, the boat is slowly returning to the
Mediterranean.
This summer we're taking it from the Red Sea
to the Mediterranean.   Do
you also work on boats?
Yes, absolutely.
And the only way to be on the boat is to
work on it every day.
You would go on a boat and then
I would continue to dedicate myself a little to
what we started with the
foundation, therefore to
cultural and artistic innovation projects.  There
are sectors that you don't do because you're
doing core work, but maybe they
would light you up.
Perhaps aerospace with the ftinque
investment in quantum computing.  There
are many sectors, then in [music]
biotech I continue to help maybe
some friends as a board member.  There are
still
many things that can be done with radioactivity.  It is still possible to create treatments that have
not yet been discovered, but above all
it is possible to create batteries that have
practically infinite lifespans,
atomic batteries, and this is perhaps something I
would like to do, but perhaps I hope to do it
with the nucleus as soon as we can as
batteries.  Are there any entrepreneurs
, living, dead, new, or old, who you admire,
like, or have
inspired you?  Elon Musk, even though he is heavily
criticized—obviously there are reasons
to criticize him—absolutely, but he
was a visionary who was able to
transform ideas into
extraordinary enterprises, so there is this aspect
here that is undeniably positive.  All
the entrepreneurs who were able to
inspire like Marchione for Fiat
too, right?
How important is it today to encourage
people to do PhD research?  It's something
I believe in very much.  Research standards
in Europe are still far
too low.
Investments in innovation are
ridiculous in Europe, so it's very
important to me that I
wanted to invest in a company that
invests in innovation like ICT,
become president, and really
help develop it.  I have
personally invested directly in other
innovating ventures because there isn't
enough of them.
What advice do you give to a guy?  In this
case we're talking about people who perhaps
study deep tech, who perhaps want to
be successful, want to have an impact, want to
believe in it all the way and fight to the
end.  Yesterday I heard a phrase
that really struck me. It was about
artists, not entrepreneurs,
but I think it's still true.  A
successful artist, I said, I have
never met an artist who wasn't
successful if he put all
the energy he deserved into it.  Let's hope that
even the young people who take on challenges,
entrepreneurship, if they put energy into it,
don't succeed.
If you had to start over from scratch today,
what would you do?   It's kind of what I've
done, but
with the knowledge I have,
I would probably leverage investors much sooner than
I actually did.   A
thousand thanks.
Thank you.
If you want to learn more about
Stefano's story, you can find the video he
made with the chapots.  Instead, on my
channel you can find a nice tour of Chern,
where we talk about microparticles,
antimatter and where Stefano worked
for many years.  And what do you think
about nuclear power?